- [Instructor] In this movie, we are going to review lists.
They are the quintessential Python container.
They provide a way to store an arbitrary number
of Python objects such as strings, floating-point numbers,
other lists, or any other object
and to access them using a numerical index.
In Python lists are denoted by brackets and their elements
are separated by commas.
The length of a list is obtained with len.
Indexing, individual list elements can be accessed by index.
Starting with zero for the first element
and ending at the length of the list minus one.
This convention of starting from zero comes from C,
the language that inspired Python
and that was used to write the standard Python interpreter
known as CPython.
For instance, the first nephew is Huey.
We can also look for the last nephew
and we can even look for a nephew beyond the end of the list
which in this case will yield an error.
We can also index from the end.
Starting at minus one and going down.
That gets us Louie and Dewey.
The bracket indexing notation,
can also be used to reassign elements.
Let's do that for all the nephews with a simple loop.
Here we're just adding their last name.
It's important to remember that lists do not need
to have homogeneous content such as all strings
or all numbers.
We can mix it up.
To add a single element at the end of the list,
we use append.
You see that here we are using Python
in an object-oriented way.
By accessing the method, specifically append,
of the list object.
It's so easy that we barely notice it.
To add multiple elements in one go, we can use extend.
To concatenate two lists, we use a plus.
That's an example of operator overloading in Python
where plus does different things for numbers and for lists.
Last, we can insert elements at any position in a list
using the insert method.
How about removing elements?
We can delete them based on their index with del
or based on the value with remove.
If we want a list sorted we can do this in place.
So we modify an existing list with sort.
Or we can make a new sorted list out of an existing one
with sorted.
Which demonstrates also how to sort backwards.
All of this should be very basic to you
if you work with Python in the past.
Moving on to slices.
Beyond working with individual list elements,
we can manipulate them in groups.
The convention is the same as for Python loops.
The first index is included, the last is not.
It's useful sometimes, to think of the indices
as being placed at the edges of the cells in a list.
We make an example based on the first few squares
of the natural numbers.
If we want the first two squares,
we'd write a slice that goes from zero to two.
There are a few more tricks that we can use in slicing.
For instance we can omit the starting index
to start at the beginning,
omit the ending index to include elements to the end.
Omit both, to get a copy of the list.
Move through the indices in steps.
And even use negative indices to count from the end.
Slices can also be used to reassign a subset of items
or to delete them.
When we introduce NumPy arrays in chapter four,
we will see that this basic slicing syntax carries over.
So it's good to understand it fully on lists first.
The empty list is written with an empty set of brackets
and obviously it has length zero.
Now for tuples, which look like lists
but with parentheses instead of brackets.
They are sometimes described as immutable versions of lists.
We can do the same indexing and slicing tricks,
but we cannot modify the elements or add new ones.
One context in which one sees tuples often
is tuple unpacking, where Python statements
or expressions are automatically evaluated in parallel
over a tuple.
For instance, to assign multiple variables at once.
The parentheses can even be omitted when there is no
room for ambiguity.
Tuples appear also when we iterate
over multiple variables at once.
For example using the enumerate iterator on a list.
Which lets us loop over list index
and list element together.
We can also unpack a tuple to pass it to a function
that requires multiple arguments such as three args.
It takes a tuple if we prefix it with an asterisk.
This ends our review of lists.