- [Instructor] While lists give us a way
to retrieve values by their index.
Python dictionary or dicts
associate keys with values.
After my imports,
let me write a simple dictionary.
Dicts are written with curly braces,
separating items with commas
and prefixing them by their key in a column.
For instance, the capitals of a few countries.
Just as we do with lists,
values are accessed with a bracket notation.
But instead of a number, we're going to use a key.
For instance,
we may wish to look at the capital of Italy.
The same notation can be used to add items to a dictionary.
Accessing a nonexistent item results in a key error.
We can also check
whether an item exists or not
with the in operator.
So we have Italy, but not Germany.
Combining two dictionaries requires
a little more thought than combining two lists.
Unlike lists, we cannot just use the plus to add them.
That's because we need to specify what happens
if both dictionaries define the same key.
What we then do is to update a dict using another,
which will replace existing items as appropriate.
This happens in place and modifies the dict.
Similarly to lists, we can delete items by key.
In fact, keys do not need to be strings.
Any Python object that is hashable may be used as a name.
Hashable means that Python can convert it to a number.
That's true for many types of objects.
For instance, tuples
which may be used to encode a birthday.
We can see the internal representation
of the keys with hash.
Just very large numbers.
The empty dictionary is written with an empty set of braces
and has length zero.
Looping over a dictionary
is very similar to looping over a list.
However, there are three different kind of loops
you may want to write.
The most straightforward syntax loops over the keys,
for key in dictionary.
Here, I'm using bold to denote language keywords.
Whereas Roman words are the names of the variables
that you will be using.
You can loop also explicitly over the keys,
you can loop over the values,
and you can loop over the keys and values together.
Let's see an example of each of these
For country in capitals,
we loop over keys.
So will for country in capitals keys.
Note that capitals dot keys is not a list,
but a special iterator object.
We can make it into a list though
by feeding it to the list constructor list.
The other two dict loops are over values, dot values,
and over keys and values together using tuple unpacking.
Beginning in Python 3.6 for the C Python interpreter,
and in python 3.7, for the very language definition,
the order of insertion is preserved for dicts.
This means then when we loop over the keys or the items,
we get them in the order
in which we originally added them to the dict.
That was not the case in previous versions of Python
and in fact, the standard library defined a special object
called order dict to preserve that order.
That is not necessary now.
Last, I want to mention sets.
You can think of them as bags of item,
which can be of mixed types
and which do not have duplications.
For instance, the continents.
Sets are written with braces, but without columns.
You can see that Africa only appears once,
even if we had it twice when we define the set.
We can check if an item exists in a set.
We can add items
or remove them
or loop over the set.
but there's no way to do indexing.
Sets and especially dicts are very important in Python,
since they underlie many aspects of the language itself.
For instance, the methods and attributes of classes
are stored internally in dicts,
and a dict key based interface is also used
in many third party packages, including pandas.
So it's very good to become familiar with them.