- [Instructor] In Python, especially when
you're dealing with data, there are many cases
where you want to iterate over a list
or a dict performing operation on every element
and then collect all the results in a new list, or dict.
You can certainly do that with a loop.
For instance, picking up the example
from the last video,
let's compute the first 10 squares,
starting with an empty list and adding
elements in the body of the loop with append.
This works, but we can do better.
We can be more pythonic, that is,
we can respect Python's specific style and spirit.
Python offers a great feature, comprehensions,
that let us write shorter,
more easily readable code,
that achieves the same effect as the loop.
In fact, the comprehension
is a compressed version of the loop.
Let's go through the steps to write one.
It's a list we want, so we have brackets.
Next, we have the loop.
And then we backtrack to the beginning of the expression
and we write code for the computation
that we want to collect.
In this case, taking the square.
The result is the same,
but we managed to write it
in a very readable and efficient way.
We can also filter the list of elements that we are creating
by adding an if clause.
For instance, we may want to collect only the squares
that are divisible by four,
which in fact, I need to do with the modulus operator.
Again, quick and readable.
In Python three, comprehension largely replace
the map and filter built-in functions,
which are important and so called functional languages,
but did not really belong in Python.
The syntax for dictionary comprehensions
is also rather intuitive.
For instance, let's create a dictionary
that will get us the square
of an integer from the integer itself.
It's a dictionary, so we need braces.
The loop part is the same
for variable and iterable.
But now, instead of the list items,
we need to write key colon value pairs.
We can also add an if clause if we want.
I don't need one here.
Here is the result in dict.
Dict comprehensions are sometimes used
to transpose an existing dict.
Going back to our capitals,
which we wrote as a dictionary index by country,
we can get the countries index by capital.
In the comprehension, we loop over the dict items,
so we get tuples of country and capital,
and we invert them by writing capital colon country.
Sometimes, you see what look like naked
comprehensions without the brackets.
Those are in fact generator expressions,
which are useful when you want to generate a sequence
and consume the elements one by one
without ever storing them in a list or a dict.
For instance, to take the sum of the first 10 squares,
we may write the interior part of our comprehension
without the brackets and feed it directly to sum.
Doing this, saves memory and time
which is important if you deal with large amounts of data.
In fact, the built-in range which we used earlier
to demonstrate loops does something very similar.
It never builds a list, but it keeps
adding new values to the loop.
If you don't currently use comprehension,
I'm sure that if you try them
you'll become addicted quickly.
And you'll start doing all sorts
of acrobatics, such as nested looping comprehensions.
For instance, look at this nested loop,
which creates a list of one,
one two, one two three,
one two three four, and so on.
We can do the same with a nested comprehension
just by writing the two loops
in the same order in sequence.
Comprehensions are incredibly useful
to manipulate lists, dicts, and data.
You should be familiar with both,
understanding and writing them.