- [Instructor] As I mentioned in the video about sequences,
tuples are similar to lists,
but we cannot change the arguments after creating the tuple.
The formal way of saying that is that tuples are immutable.
Tuples are very useful to store data records
when we think that we are not going to modify the values.
For instance, a list of people with their first names,
last names, and birthdays.
For each element in this list, for each person,
we access the data fields by index.
Zero for the name, one for the family name.
This lets us write useful list comprehensions.
For instance, to find all the people
with a given birthday.
We loop over every person in People,
and for each we check if the third element
of the tuple, index two, is July 15.
I share a birthday with a very famous astronomer,
Jocelyn Bell Burnell.
Field access by index means that
we have to remember which is which,
creating the potential for bugs,
and certainly reducing the expressiveness of our code.
To help us out, the module Collections
in the standard Python library offers
a name tuple that lets you create a specialized object,
a specialized tuple, that has a name and that
associates labels with fields.
For instance, a person type would be called Person
and have fields first name, last name, and birthday.
We can then create instances of the Name tuple
by using the type and giving the field values sequentially.
Or we can even use the field names,
which lets us shuffle the fields if we need to.
Name tuples have the advantage that they print nicely.
Now let's look at accessing the fields.
Indices still work.
So we get a zero, one and two gives me
first name, last name, and birthday.
But field names using the object-oriented DOS syntax
are now what we're going to use,
because they make our intentions clear in the code we write.
Let's convert our little database to name tuples.
We can't use a standard tuple directly
and feed it person type, because person type
needs three arguments.
Here, Python is complaining that two are missing.
So this is a case where tuple unpacking comes useful.
I use a star to unpack tuple zero into its three elements.
To do all of them, we will, of course,
use a list comprehension.
Now our birthday search reads better.
It shows me explicitly that I'm looking at
the birthday field of each tuple.
Python 3.7 introduced an alternative
to tuples index for storing data records, data classes.
To use them, we need to import data class
from the data classes module.
If you are for some reason in Python 3.6,
you can still use data classes,
but you need to install them explicitly as a package.
For instance, with PIP Install.
So I do my import, and this is how we would
set up a personal record with first name, a string,
last name, a string, and a birthday,
and say again a string,
with the default value for the birthday.
If you're not familiar with Python classes,
class decorators, the At data class that appears at the top,
and if you're not familiar with that annotation
the syntax will look somewhat alien.
But basically, we're instructing Python
to create the type of records that will have fields
called first name, last name, and birthday,
all of which will be strings.
We'll create an instance of this class, a person,
making the fields sequentially or by keywords.
You see here that the field of that known birthday
is applied, since I didn't provide a birthday
to the definition.
We can access the field by name but not by index.
And again, the data class prints nicely.
In contrast to name tuple,
data classes are full Python classes,
so we can define methods that operate on the fields,
such as a method that returns a person's full name.
If you're not familiar with object-oriented
programming in Python, do not worry.
We will not need this feature in what follows.
Nevertheless, for person class two,
calling full name as a method runs the code that we wrote
and returns my full name.
Data classes have many other useful features,
such as freezing, disallowing modifications,
ordering, allowing the comparison of class instances,
defining data classes by inheritance, and a lot more.
So I encourage you to learn more about them
if you are somewhat familiar with
object-oriented programming
and specifically classes in Python.
Now we move on to our last topic
about data extractions in Python.
In a video about dict, I discussed how
a special variant of dictionary,
collections order dict, is now much less useful
because the standard dict preserves the order
in which elements were inserted.
There's another variant of dict that remains useful,
collections default dict.
The point here is to define a default for values
that will be returned if we ask for a key
for which there was no entry.
More precisely, we have to provide a function
that returns that default.
Let me write out the function that we will use.
We'll call it mydefault, and it will return a simple string.
So here's my default dict.
If I go in and ask for a key that doesn't exist yet,
I will just get the default back.
Not only, that key will be now part of the dictionary.
This makes default dict useful
when we want to build a dictionary
where each key can correspond to a list of items.
Let's make an example based on birthdays.
With standard dict, we need to write code
that behaves differently if the birthday
has been seen already, and then we can append
to the list of people with the same birthday
or if the birthday has not been seen,
in which case we need to create a list with one element.
That is quite inconvenient.
The repetition of code is annoying and prone to bugs.
We'll use the full dict instead,
and we will take advantage of the fact
that list called as a function returns the empty list.
So we can use it to provide a default.
Thus, we can write birthdays
as collection_defaultdict
with list as the default maker,
and then simply look over person in our name tuple
and constraint to get in that key the birthday
and appending to the resulting list.
There are more useful container types
in the standard library module collections.
I encourage you to look them up
and to use them in your work instead of
reinventing those wheels.