- [Instructor] Pandas has gained broad acceptance
in the Python community
as the data analysis tool for Python.
As of January 2020,
it should reach version 1.0 very soon,
signaling the stability of its API,
its programming interface.
Pandas is built on top of NumPy so it's very fast.
And it extends NumPy in ways that are extremely useful
to data analysis.
For instance it attaches labels to table columns and rows.
It lets us access data using indexes
built from any variable.
It allows us to modify table structure
by adding and dropping columns
and by performing other transformations.
It recognizes many common data formats.
It handles missing data easily.
It implements database operations such as joins
and it can even make plots.
So if you want to do data analysis
or data science with Python,
I really recommend that you learn Pandas.