- [Instructor] The two key objects in pandas
are the DataFrame and the Series.
A DataFrame is basically a table of data.
Each column has a name and an assigned data type as a NumPy.
In addition though, the DataFrame has an index,
which is not necessarily the ordinal number of the row.
In this example, where the columns contain name,
date of birth and city, the index could be
the social security number or an alphanumerical employee ID.
A Series is effectively a single column
from a DataFrame with its own index.
Having an index makes it more powerful
than a simple NumPy array.
For instance, if we have two time Series
that have partially overlapping indices, times,
we can still combine them and pandas will figure out
which entries it can actually compute.
Just as for NumPy arrays the easiest way
to get a pandas DataFrame is to load it from a file.
And pandas can read and write
an even larger variety of formats than NumPy
These include ASCII tables, json, Excel,
the hierarchical data format HDF
using many scientific application, SAS, SAS, Strata,
Big data storage formats, such as Apache Feather and Parquet
SQL and even HTML tables, which is great
if you want to scrape data from a website.
In this table, I show you the formats
with the pandas functions that read and write them.
Some of them may require the assistance of another package
that you need to install separately.
We start with a simple text file.
Nobels.CSV, which contains a list of Nobel Laureates
with a year in discipline
in which they were awarded their prize.
We can have a look.
This is quite simple, the values are separated by commas.
Pandas read CSV with this without breaking a sweat.
We do need to provide names for the columns
since the file itself doesn't have that information.
Read CSV has many other options
including specifying separators other than commerce,
skipping columns or rows, converting dates and more.
Let's look at the DataFrame.
The method Info gives us basic information.
And the method Head prints the first few rows,
Tail the last.
We have a total of 950 records.
And we see that indeed the columns are named year
discipline and the Nobelist.
The data types are integer for the year
and Python object for discipline and Nobelist.
That's an important observation while in NumPy,
we represent strings as fixed with runs of characters.
In panda strings are effectively the immutable strings
of Python, which are more versatile.
As I mentioned, the index plays a very important role
for data frames, but this one in particular,
is a boring Numerical index.
To grab the individual columns, which become Series,
we use a dict like syntax with brackets,
or a class like syntax with dot.
Either way, the result is a pandas series,
the object there represents a column.
Consequently, the series has a name, ID type,
and it carries with it the index of the original DataFrame.
If we need a naked NumPy array of the values,
we can still get it with dot values.
Here's a small slice.
Sometimes it's useful to get a list or really a NumPy array
of all the unique values in a column.
Other times, it's useful to have counts of the times
each item appears.
This accounting confirms that three scientists
were awarded two prizes.
To select records, we can use fancy indexing,
building a Boolean expression that involves the columns.
For instance, select the Nobels in Physics.
Or you can use the convenient and fast Query Interface
which takes a logical expression given as a string.
We have to mind our quotes here making sure that we use
single quotes for the query
and double quotes for any values inside it.
Sometimes it's not evident how to write
a filtering operation.
For instance, if we seek all the Nobelists
whose name contain Curie, we like to write
something like this, Nobel's fancy indexed by Curie
in Nobel's Nobelist but that fails quite spectacularly.
Instead we need to dig down in the string methods
supported by the series to find Contains,
which does what we need.
The selection confers incredible winning streak
of the Curie family.
Marie her husband Pierre,
her daughter Irine and her son in law Frederic
Be sure how to create a data frame yourself.
First from a NumPy record array.
For instance, the David Bowie discography
that we use as an example in chapter four.
This is almost like cheating because NumPy record arrays
are in fact the very back end of pandas.
Nevertheless, the fixed length strings
are converted to Python objects, when we get a DataFrame.
Starting from scratch, we may build a DataFrame
from a list of dictionaries, which means
that we'll be repeating the column names over and over.
Or from a list of tuples by providing names for the columns
here title and top rank.
Name tuples would also work great here.
Otherwise, we can build the DataFrame in the other direction
from a dictionary of vectors or lists.
Here I'm just copying information
from the NumPy record array to make actual lists.
And then I feed them to DataFrame.
We have DataFrames, let's move on to using them.
Now that we know how to load or make DataFrames,
let's do something interesting with them.