- [Instructor] We have seen how to load
and create dataframes
and how to select records based on boolean conditions
both with fancy indexing
and with a string expression-based query interface.
Now we'll see how we can make selections even more directly
and more efficiently using indices.
So let's load up our Nobel list data set again.
The index is currently the simplest possible
just numbers from zero through 949.
We elevate the years to serve as index.
We do this with a set index method
which does not work in place
but other creates a new dataframe.
Now the years appear as the index
at the front of each row.
And here's the index itself.
This shows that in Pandas,
indices do not need to have unique values.
That's a feature, not a bug.
It lets us select all records for a year, for instance,
using the indexing notation
and here things get a bit complicated.
There are several ways to do indexing and slicing in Pandas,
some equivalent to each other, some not.
I'm going to show you the two interfaces
that I think are the least confusing.
To select all records for a given index,
we use .loc followed by brackets, not parentheses,
with the index value.
For instance, 1901.
We can also add a column name
just as if we were selecting a cell in a numpy array.
The result is a series.
In addition to selecting individual index values
.loc allows for slices.
But in a break from Python new search,
the range is inclusive of its end value.
If we choose the years of the great war, 1914-1918,
then 1918 appears in the selection.
We are not limited to all micro-indices.
We can set up a dataframe
indexed by discipline, for instance.
And it's always best to keep the index sorted
which we do with sort_index.
Then we can select not just individual index values,
but also ranges, which again, are inclusive.
So physics,
or medicine through peace.
Here there are 353 rows
but Pandas is only showing us a few at the beginning
and at the end.
That's what the ellipses symbols mean in the middle.
If you want numpy style indexing,
looking only the progressive count of the records,
you can have it with .iloc, again, brackets.
Here we get the first 10 records, whatever they are,
in the dataframe in its current order.
But this is not the end of the story.
Pandas supports multi indices.
For instance, a dataframe indices nobelists by year first,
and then discipline.
It looks like this.
The underlying index is a very complicated beast.
But we can isolate the values set at two levels
using, appropriately, get level values.
Armed with this multi-index dataframe,
we can select records by both year and discipline.
Passing it two-pole to .loc.
For instance, physics and 2017.
Slicing however, can get complicated.
Say we want chemistry prizes between 1901 and 1910.
What we would like to do is to write a slice
with a column in a two-pole.
But Python doesn't allow that.
How about we use the long-hand expression for the slice?
Slice by indices start and end value.
That's still confusing to Pandas
because then it tries to use chemistry as a column name.
What works is to request the set of columns
explicitly in the .loc expression.
In this case, all of them with a comma.
Fancy indexing works also.
Here, slice none means that we're taking all the years
but we select a list of the disciplines.
And again, all the fields.
Finally, while multi-indexing is powerful,
it can be confusing.
And so you may have to resort to trial and error.
Any selection that you make that way, however,
you can also achieve without multi-indexing
by using criteria on the values in the columns.
For instance, chemistry prizes between 1901 and 1910.
Where I have built a three boolean arrays,
years are going to equal the 1901,
years less or equal to 1910,
and discipline equals equals chemistry
and I have taken the logical end with the ampersand.
Or again, with query,
which lets me write the same selection
in a more intuitive form.
Note, however, that all these queries return new dataframes.
So you cannot use them to modify values
in the original table as you could do with the indices.