- [Instructor] We have seen how to load
and create data frames, and how to select records
or ranges of records, but we have not done much
with the values in the tables.
In many data analysis tasks, you're interested
in running computations with the columns
and then making plots.
Let's try that with Pandas.
We'll load the data set consisting
of global population health and wealth statistics,
from the amazing Gapminder website.
Gapminder is a Swedish foundation created
by the late Hans Rosling to promote a fact-based worldview
and to fight misconceptions about global development.
If you want to make plots in the Gapminder style
internalize their data in some depth,
you can try my LinkedIn learning course,
Python Statistics Essential Training.
In this video we'll do simpler things
but still learn a lot.
So we load the comma-separated file.
And we see that the data set includes a number
of global statistics.
Each row identifies a country, a year,
the corresponding region, and then they count us
population, life expectancy, the percentage
of children born alive who survive to age five,
the average number of babies per fertile woman
and the domestic product per person in 2011 dollars.
We can ask Pandas to compute single statistics
on all the fields.
We do that with data frame describe.
We see that there are almost 15,000 records
in the data set for years ranging from 1800 to 2015.
We can read off the minimum, maximum, mean,
and standard deviation for all the fields
as well as the 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles.
If you don't know about these don't worry.
They give us an idea of the typical values
and typical range of variation of a quantity.
One of the points that Gapminder makes to great effect
is that life expectancy improves with wealth,
the Gross Domestic Product per person, GDP,
and that the correlation is even clear
if we look at the logarithm of the GDP per person per day.
We don't have a column with that information,
but it's very easy to compute it and to store
it in a new data frame column.
So we divide GDP per capita by the average number
of days in a year, apply a non-pi log 10,
and store that in a new column which then appears
in the data frame.
To see global trends as a function of time
or to examine individual countries,
it makes sense to index by year and then country.
We will have two versions of the data frame
with those two indices.
Pandas has its own plotting interface
which focuses on choosing the variables with which to plot.
Say for instance we want to show life expectancy
is a function of log GDP.
So we select data for 1960 with dot log,
and then generate a scatter plot of those two variables,
it's sufficient to give the column names to Pandas.
If we want to compare a more recent year in the same plot,
we need to grab a map of lib axis object from the first plot
and then pass it to the second.
This is the kind of solution you find
on http://www.stackoverflow.com.
You should also change colors
and label the two clouds of points.
We see that in going between 1960
and 2015, the dots flatten towards the top,
towards higher life-expectancies.
Thanks to significant progress
in public health policy and practice.
The trend is the same for other statistical indicators
such as survival by age five.
The data frame index by country lets us make easy plots
of the chronological evolution of an indicator
such as life expectancy for a country such as Italy.
But the result is jumbled
if we don't first sort the values by year.
I'll do it here with sort values.
The style of coding where I concatenate one Pandas method
after the other is in fact quite idiomatic for Pandas,
if not for Python.
So when we say that Pandas speaks
its own Python dialect.
Here's a comparative plot for three countries.
Again we grab the math.lib axis and pass them
to the second or third plots.
We see that Italy caught up with the United States
in terms of life expectancy and China is coming close
after the disastrous 1960 famine.
Another interesting and important correlation
was between fertility rate and survival to age five.
To look at this question globally we can compute the average
fertility rate over all records,
that however doesn't mean much,
since it misses data from many years.
We can use the Panda's group by functionality
to segment the data frame by year
before computing the average.
The result is a series indexed by year
which shows the average fertility rate as a function of time
and we plot it against age five survival,
treated in the same fashion.
The Pandas plot allows us to add a second axis
on the right to show the range of the second variable
that we plot.
This shows forcefully that high natality
is a consequence of infant mortality,
and that women have many fewer children
when they believe they will survive.
On a small scale, we see that post 1950 baby boom.
To gain even more insight we can create a pivot table.
This segments the fertility means by both year
and geographical region.
Pandas is very happy to plot the resulting timelines.
The drop in fertility came after the baby boom
for Africa, America, and Asia.
Europe was already low and decreasing
since the beginning of the 20th century.
And here's the corresponding plot for age five survival.
Africa is now roughly where Europe was in 1950.
Using Pandas plotting functions is the quickest way
to make insightful statistical illustrations.
But for maximum flexibility,
you can always extract the values
from the frames as non-pras
and pass those to standard math.lib functions,
which are fully customizable.
There's a lot more you can do in Pandas,
and there's a lot more to learn
that I can cover in this course.
I try instead to give you a feel
for what is possible and practical.
I encourage you to start working
on a data set that interests you
and to pick up more techniques and knowledge
using the many resources available on the web.