- Well done.
Thank you for following along
through some rather challenging material.
You are at the start of your road to mastery.
You can now move on to my more advanced courses
on programming efficiently in Python
and on statistics with Python.
Back to the topic of this course,
here are some resources that can help you learn more.
You can find the answer to any question about Python
or about NumPy, Matploylib and pandas
on the official websites.
These packages are also discussed in
"Python Data Science Handbook" by Jake Vanderplas,
a very insightful and no-nonsense textbook.
If you get stuck, look for help
in an internet forum such as Stack Overflow.
You'll find that Python has a very helpful
and supportive community.
Many have said that the best thing about Python
is that it's a language that makes you happy.
I agree so have fun and do great things.