- [Instructor] In this chapter, we introduce NumPy,
a third-party package for Python
that extends the language with multi-dimensional arrays
that are fast, memory-efficient,
and that can manage very large data sets.
NumPy is an important part of the Python ecosystem.
It has become a fundamental package for data analysis,
and for any kind of mathematical application with Python.
Let's talk about how NumPy arrays are different
from Python containers, such as lists.
Python variables are often described as labels.
They are not little boxes in computer memory
ready to receive a value.
Rather, the values are independent objects
with their own space in memory,
and Python variables are labels or names
that are attached to the values.
So you can have more than one variable,
referring to the same object.
It's a very flexible mechanism,
and it makes it possible to have lists and dictionaries
with heterogenous elements.
However, it's not very efficient when we need to
deal with many values of the same type.
In that case, you want to reserve space in memory,
and store all the values side by side,
and that's exactly what a NumPy array is.
Organizing data in this way
is both faster and more efficient in memory.
It's also a necessary step if you want to
interface Python with other languages,
such as C or Fortran,
which count on data being laid out in memory like this.
In this slide, I'm showing you a schematic representation
of a one dimensional and a two dimensional array.
The actual data items sit side by side in memory,
and they all have the same size.
If there is one dimensional,
we identify items by a single index,
or two indices for a two dimensional array.
The index ranges from 0 to one minus one,
where N is the dimensional array.
In the case of a two dimensional array,
the dimensions can be different of course.
Since, as we said, all the data items in an array
need to have the same size,
NumPy needs to be very precise about identifying data types.
In fact, more precise than Python.
While Python has just one type of integer,
and one type of floating-point number,
NumPY has several.
NumPY identifies different types of integers,
dependent on the number of bits
that each of them takes up in memory,
int8, int16, int32, and int64 the most common.
There are also unsigned version of the integers.
As for floating-point numbers,
we have float16, 32, 64, and on some platforms 128.
The most common is float64.
There are other more special I-Types,
complex numbers, booleans, true or false,
bytes, unicode strings,
for which you need to specify lengths,
void, used for record arrays,
and object, which is in effect a pointer
to arbitrary Python objects.
So let's see NumPY arrays in action.