- [Instructor] The easiest way to get
a NumPy array is to load it from a file.
NumPy recognizes several file formats,
including, of course, simple text files.
I have prepared one for you
that describes a very well-known painting.
The file is called monalisa.txt
and it's included in your exercise files
in the same directory as this notebook.
Let's have a look at the content.
We open the file with open in reading mode,
and we use the readlines method
to get all the lines of the file.
So we see that we have 200 lines
and that each line is a sequence of integers.
NumPy loads the file without any trouble using loadtxt.
The result is a two-dimensional array.
If we display it, NumPy omits some rows and columns
so it fits on the screen.
We can query the object, the array,
for the number of dimensions, which are two,
the shape, which is 200 by 134,
200 rows by 134 columns,
the total number of elements,
and the type of element.
In this case it's the very common 64 bit
floating point number.
Okay, so we have a two-dimensional array called monalisa.
I wonder, is it an image that we can display?
We can use the Matplotlib function imshow
to display two-dimensional arrays as images.
Although, we should perhaps use a better column map,
such as gray.
I've also prepared a colored version of the painting
and I have saved it in NumPy's native binary format,
which works across all platforms.
The file is monalisa.mpy.
This is now a three-dimensional array,
where the last dimension is used to store
red, green and blue components.
Imshow understands this without any problem.
We have lots of pixels, so we can make the image bigger
by instructing Matplotlib to have a larger figure size.
Five by eight refers to inches,
although how that turns out in pixels
depend on the resolution of your screen.
We now know how to load the NumPy array.
How about making one ourselves?
The easiest way is to take a Python list
or a nested list of lists and pass it to NumPy array.
The data type is automatically set.
And we can query the object as we did before.
Another common way to create
an array is to make an empty one.
We give the shape and the data type.
For instance, we can do a one-dimensional array
a vector of length eight.
Here d is just a shorthand for a float 64, an 8-byte float.
We can do a two-dimensional array, a matrix.
And we can query these objects for their metadata,
and plot them on the same line.
It is sometimes useful to make an array of zeros
in the shape of another existing array.
That's done with zeroes_like.
Otherwise, we can make a really empty array.
Here, the memory is allocated, but not even cleaned,
so we get some nonsensical values.
We can also create a regularly spaced array
of number with linspace with specified extrema,
for instance, zero and one,
and the total number of elements, here 16.
We can't show a one-dimensional array as an image,
but we can certainly plot it with Matplotlib.
Here, I will use a thick marker
as specified by lowercase o.
Instead of choosing the number of elements
between two extrema as we did with linspace,
we can use NumPy arange, which has the same convention
as Python's built-in range.
In this case, we have elements
between zero and 1.5 spaced by 0.1.
NumPy can also give us an array of random numbers.
We just need to specify the shape.
By default, we get numbers uniformly distributed
between zero and one.
If we plot them with color, they look suitably random.
We could also use random.randint and NumPy random.randn
to get either integers in a given range
or normally distributed numbers.
To close this video, let me show you
how to save an array to a file.
Np.save will create a cross-platform binary file.
The file ending is conventionally .mpy,
but it doesn't need to be.
Numpy savetext, instead, will create a readable ASCII table.
And if we load it, we see that it's all there.
Now that we've created our arrays,
let's see what we can do with them.