- [Instructor] Let's see how we can access
individual elements and ranges of elements in NumPy.
We will demonstrate on our good old friend Mona Lisa.
So let me load up the file.
I remind you, this is a three-dimensional NumPy array
with dimensions that correspond to
height 1198 pixels with 804,
and color three, for red, green and blue.
Imgshow shows us the picture.
The syntax to get that individual pixels
is just an extension of Python list indexing,
except that we can now include
multiple indices among brackets.
For instance, a point roughly in the middle
would be on row 600, column 400
and we grabbed the red component.
If we wish to go to the bottom right corner,
we may count back from the boundary of the array,
just that we would do for a list.
This should be the same as
1148, 754 and one.
If we try to index elements beyond the boundary,
we get an index error.
And of course, we can use indexing to assign values
to the elements.
Once you get used to multi-indexing like this,
you'll have the temptation of trying it
on nested Python lists,
but there it doesn't work.
So let me demonstrate with a rather uninspired list.
We cannot ask for element one comma two,
rather, we need to ask for list number one,
and then element two.
One more reason to like NumPy arrays.
Slicing also works in a very similar way to Python lists.
For instance, we could grab a section
in the middle of the painting
from rows 400 to 800, columns 200 to 600s.
Here's the detail.
Often we want to grab the entire range
over one or more axes, in which case,
we can use the shorthand column for the full slice.
There's an even shorter hand
for multiple full slices, ellipses sign.
We can also specify a step,
which has the effect of reducing the resolution
of the picture
because we've taken every 20th pixel.
See the black dot in the middle?
It's there because earlier we assigned zero
to all three color channels for pixel 600 and 400,
the single pixel was invisible at higher resolution,
but it's one of those selected by this slice
with steps of 20.
How about slicing backwards?
That works too.
And in this case, it inverts the rows.
And if we mix slicing and indexing,
we reduce the dimensionality of the array.
In this case, it becomes just a vector.
We can show a vector as an image or we can plot it.
Note that fixing one of the indices
is not the same as asking for a slice of one.
In that case, the array remains two-dimensional.
Slicing can also be used on the left side
of an assignment statement.
We can use this to modify elements in bulk,
such as deleting a square in the top corner of the image.
Doing so, assign the same value to all the pixels there.
But we can also match slices on both sides
of the assignment.
So let's replace the white square
with a random set of pixels.
NumPy arrays also support
an especially useful form of indexing
that is not available with lists.
This is known as fancy indexing.
It means that we're using arrays to index another array.
To demonstrate that,
let me grab my lower resolution grayscale image.
I'm going to threshold this image
by first figuring out all the pixels
that are darker than a certain value.
The result is a two-dimensional Boolean array,
the same size as monalisa_bw.
I can then use this Boolean array
to select the corresponding subset of pixels
and modify only those.
Here's the thresholded image.
Finally, let me point out another very important difference
between lists and NumPy arrays.
Whenever you slice a list, you make a copy of it.
Say I have a simple list of six elements
and I take a slice of the first four.
Assigning to the slice does not modify the original list.
By contrast, a slice of a NumPy array
is a new NumPy object
that points to the same area of memory,
but we modified meta data that represents
the different boundaries.
So if I assigned to the slides,
I'm also assigning to the underlying object.
If we want a true copy pointing to new memory,
you have to make the copy explicitly.
Acting on the copy does not affect the original.