- [Instructor] NumPy is extremely useful
in numerical calculations.
That's because in addition to packing numbers
efficient in memory, NumPy makes it easy
to perform mathematical operations
with entire arrays.
For instance, in a study of mathematical functions,
we may start with a vector of equally-spaced real values
between say zero and five times pi.
Here it is.
Note that with the list space, the extreme of zero
and five pi are included.
Then we may want to complete the sine
of all these values.
We cannot do this with a function
in the standard math library.
Math dot sin.
But we can with the NumPy version,
which is called the universal function for this reason.
It can operate on any array, in element by element fashion.
There is always another NumPy array
with the same shape as X.
Using map dot lib, I can now plot sine X against X.
Specifying first the coordinates along the horizontal axis
and then the coordinates along the vertical.
Map dot lib takes care of setting the Y range automatically.
By repeating the plot statement,
I can show multiple functions together.
Map dot lib will automatically cycle through colors
so it can distinguish the lines.
So let's try our sine together with a cosine
and then logarithm.
We can add labels to remind us which is which,
and then collect the labels in a legend.
There are many more options in map dot lib
regarding the style of the lines,
the formatting of the plot, and more.
You can look at the documentation to learn more.
We can also perform operations
that involve more than one array
and everything goes smoothly if we match array shapes.
So let's make the cosine in addition of the sine,
and let's try combining the two.
By contrast, operations between arrays of different shapes
generally fail.
NumPy doesn't quite know what to do.
There is one important exception,
which is known as broadcasting.
NumPy, when it can, makes sense of operations
between arrays of different dimensions
rather than shapes.
The simplest case, which is rather intuitive,
is just to add a single number to an entire array.
We see that W is offset by 1.5 with respect to sine X.
The plot would also be self-explanatory.
Let's go up to two dimensions
and then we'll straighten our friend, the Mona Lisa.
The image is 200 rows by 134 columns.
I can multiply every column by a different number
by making a vector of length 134.
In this case, NumPy matches the second dimension
of the array, with a single dimension of the vector.
I want to show you the result
side by side with the original image.
So I need to do a little work with math dot lib.
I will start with a larger figure size,
figure and fix size,
and then I set up one row
with two plots using subplot.
The arguments to subplot go one row, two columns,
and then the subplot that I want to make.
Multiplying the array in this way
had the effect of applying horizontal gradient.
What about the other way around?
If I make a vector of length 200,
you'd think we could apply it on the left
to multiply every row by a single value.
That however doesn't work.
What works is to add a new dimension of length one
to the gradient vector, which we can do
with a special indexing notation, NP dot new axis.
The shape of Y grad is now 200 by one.
NumPy broadcasting then matches the first dimension
of the two arrays, Mona Lisa BW and Y grad,
and broadcasts the second dimension of Y grad
to fill up the corresponding range in Mona Lisa.
The result is the vertical gradient.
NumPy supports many other useful mathematical operations,
including fast fully transforms, random numbers,
statistics, interpolation, and linear algebra.
If you need any of them,
you can go read the NumPy documentation.
There is one thing I want to show you here.
It's that since version 3.5,
Python implements a special matrix multiplication operator.
The at symbol, which is put to good use by NumPy.
For instance, we can use it
to make the dot product of two vectors.
A and B, each of three elements.
This is the same as writing NumPy dot dot AB.
Or we could write the products of a three by three matrix
in a three vector.