- [Instructor] In the last video for this chapter,
I want to show you two NumPy features
that are not always covered in tutorials,
but they're still very useful.
One is record arrays, where we can mix different data types
and give descriptive names to fields.
The other is date time objects,
which as the name says, can encode a date and time.
Let us load up a simple example of a record array,
which I have prepared in the NumPy binary format.
This is a partial David Bowie discography.
Each entry shows the record name, the date of release
and the top rank in the UK charts.
Let's look at the data type.
It's a list which shows the name of each field
and the actual D type.
For title, it's U32, which denotes a Unicode string
of maximum length 32.
For release, it's M eight brackets D
which denotes a date time object with granularity of days.
It could be as small as a nanosecond in fact.
The eight refers to the size in bytes
of each date time object.
Last, the top rank, is an eight byte integer data type.
If you're wondering about the less symbol in each of these,
those refer to the endianness of the data types,
the order in which the bytes are stored in memory.
Inter-processors are little endian.
So what can we do with a record array?
Each record looks like a Python tuple,
and we can extract the elements as we would for a tuple
but we can also modify them.
We can also use a dict like interface
using the field names in brackets.
This, in fact, will also get us a full column.
To create a record array,
you have to be a little careful in specifying the D type.
It's useful to go read about data type descriptors
in the NumPy documentation.
But let's try one.
We specify a subset of the information
we have in discography, just the title and release date.
This array is empty right now,
but we can copy over the two columns.
Here we see that the title strings
have been truncated to 16 characters.
Since all the data is stored contiguously in memory,
the lengths that we prescribe for the fields
are very important and set the limit for the data
that we can store.
We see also that we specified a finer granularity
for the date time object, seconds,
although it's all zeros because the discography array
didn't have that information.
We move on to the date time object,
which is called datetime64
to avoid confusion with the object in the standard library,
and also to remind us that each element takes 64 bits.
We can initialize date time object with strings,
and we can give it as much detail as we want,
just the year, a full date,
and date and hour minute combination, or even beyond that.
Date times can be compared,
so noon came before 6 p.m. on that day, like any day.
Date times can also be subtracted,
resulting in a time delta object,
which here is specified in minutes.
The nice thing about these date time objects
is that they are understood across NumPy.
For instance, we can use the NumPy function diff,
which computes the differences between
successive elements of a vector
to see how long it took David Bowie
to come up with a new record after each one.
Ziggy Stardust was especially quick.
Another example may be making a range of these.
NumPy in a range understand date times.
And we see that the last day is excluded
consistently with the conventions of range and a range.
This functionality is extended even further in Pandas.
And in fact, the whole idea of record arrays
has a much stronger implementation in Pandas DataFrames.
We'll learn about those later in this course.