- [Instructor] You can download the Social Security
name data set from their website.
But I have also included the archive names.zip
in your exercise files.
We need to uncompress it,
which we can do in Python using the ZipFile module.
The interface is object oriented.
You first create a ZipFile object,
then called extract all in the current directory.
That's the dot.
Jupiter lets us browse the contents
of the current directory with ls.
We see that names.zip,
unpacked into a directory with many text files,
presumably one for every year.
Let's have a look at one.
We open it in read mode
and print out the first few lines.
It's a very simple comma separated format.
Name, sex, presumably F or M,
and then the number of babies born that year with that name.
Pandas read CSV shouldn't have any problems.
But we did do something wrong.
The first record in the file, Sofia,
was used to set the names of the columns.
We need to provide the column names explicitly,
since they're not in the file.
We've already done this for the Nobel data set.
Better.
We will need to load all the tables
and concatenate them in a single data frame.
To avoid confusing data from different years,
we can prepare the individual data frames
by adding a new column that specifies the year.
To do it on the fly, directly from the output of read CSV,
by chaining a method,
we can use data frame assign.
In this case, a new column year appears with value 2011.
Excellent.
We managed to load the file in a one liner,
so you can see that I'm going to use a comprehension
to concatenate all the data frames.
There are several things happening here.
So let's look at this carefully.
We loop over all the years between 1880 and 2018.
We build up the file name using an f-string,
and feed that to read CSV.
We specify the column names,
and we add the column that gives the correct year
from the loop variable.
Finally, we pass all the resulting data frames
to pd concat, pandas concat.
You see there are no brackets here,
so this is in fact a generator expression,
not the comprehension,
which pd concat accepts quite happily.
It's a very efficient way to build a data frame,
and it's all there.
Almost two million entries.
The year range is what we expect.
We can save the merged data frame using to CSV.
We don't need to say the index
and if we specify a file name that ends in .gz,
the resulting file will be automatically compressed.