- [Instructor] We are ready to start analyzing this data.
How we load and look
at the combined data frame we just created.
We want to examine the change in popularity of a name.
So we need to reframe the data in a way,
that will make this easier.
We will use a multi-index.
We will index the date on sex first,
then name, and then year.
And we will also sort the index.
Getting the data for any given name
is then a simple exercise
of indexing with dot loc.
For instance Mary,
this series is ready to plot.
Notice how Metro-lib automatically uses
the index to set the x-axis.
We see two peaks.
At approximately 1920 and 1950.
It probably makes sense also
to consider the frequency of a name as a fraction
of the number of babies born in a year.
To get that, we can apply group by
on the un-indexed data frame and take the sum.
Then we can normalize Mary
by all the newborns in every year.
So as a percentage of all babies,
Mary was actually more popular
at the beginning of the 20th century.
But there were altogether
more Marys born in the 1920s and 50s.
For simplicity, we continue with unnormalized counts.
So let's make a generic function plot name
to make a plot like this.
In another function compare names
to plot a few names together.
You see that we pass a list of names through compare names.
We look over the list called plot name for each of them
and then add a legend, which is always good.
Let's for instance compare Michael, John, David and Martin.
Or for girls Emily, Anna, Claire and Elizabeth.
It's already a popularity contest that we make in here.
Another interesting investigations
is to compare variance of the same name.
For instance, there are two spellings of Claire.
There's an older version Clara,
and an Italian and Irish spelling
for the pronunciation Ciara.
Here's the plot.
Notice how Metro-lib tries to put the legend out of the way.
Claire is now dominant,
but Clara is having a resurgance
after having been the dominant variant
at the beginning of the 20th century.
We can make a slightly different cumulative
or stacked plot that adds up the counts
on top of each other.
For that, we need a table of the frequencies
for all the variance as a function of time.
That would be an exercise in multi-indexing.
We start by selecting all the Claires
and then we can apply data frame and stack
to move one of the index levels to a column name.
In this case the year is level two of the multi-index.
So the years become the columns.
I must say that sometimes it's hard to make sense
of what unstack does, so expect some trial and error.
By contrast, unstacking level one
would have made columns corresponding to the name variance.
We can now try this stack plot.
On the x-axis we will have the years
just a simple range will suffice.
And on the y-axis, the stacked values.
This works but we see that the plot
is truncated around 1974.
That must be because of some of the Nans in the table,
which do not lend themselves to be summed up.
That's easy to fix
with data frame fill and A.
We'll replace the Nans with zeros.
And here's the final plot.
I have also added a legend,
seeded by the labels given to stack plot.
And I've restricted the x-axis,
quite nice and informative.
Except perhaps for the garish different colors
chosen by map plot lib.