- [Instructor] In this video,
we will create yearly top 10s for male and female names.
We load the data, and this time,
we index it slightly differently, by sex and year only
since we will need to compare all the names in the database.
We now build up a query by chaining pandas methods.
Getting males in 2018
is a simple matter of a multiindex.log.
Then we get the most popular names
by sorting our number in descending order.
Head gives us a top 10.
In 2018, Liam was king, followed closely by Noah.
How about girls?
We index sex with f, and the year is still 2018.
For girls, it was Emma and Olivia.
If we to build a table of the top 10 names
over multiple years,
we should get rid of the index with Reset Index,
and select the name, Column Only.
I will make this into a generic function.
As I was saying, in pandas,
one sees this operator chaining style often.
And we can make the code clear
by giving each method it's own line.
It's a good idea, however, to add comments
to explain what you're doing,
either for your collaborators or your future self
since pandas can be obscure.
To form a table,
we collect the series for different years
as the columns of the data frame, labeled by the year.
So in effect,
we're creating a data frame from a dict comprehension.
For males, you can see Liam gaining popularity
and Jacob dropping.
For females, we see that Emma has been dominant
for a few years while Sophia dropped.
Olivia is there, waiting to take the crown.
How about the popularity plot for the 2018 top 10?
For a change, we'll use the query interface,
which conveniently lets us use the values of variables
with the Add Notation.
So here, we're passing sex and name to the function.
And we select in All The Records
where the sex column equals the sex argument,
and the name column equals the name argument.
This is not very pythonic,
but it's nice to have once you know about it.
Once we have the records, we plot number against year.
So let's loop over the 2018 female top 10 and plot each.
It's interesting to see
that all the top names seem to have surged quite recently
except perhaps for Evelyn, which was popular in the 1920s.
As for the male names, two are classics, William and James.
Let's look at the others then.
This is the list, and I will copy
a subset of it to the loop over which I plot.
So now, I'm excluding William and James.
And I see that, yes, the other eight
have also been recent discoveries.
How about all-time favorites?
We get there quickly by selecting females, say,
grouping by name, summing the numbers,
sorting by the values, and then taking the top 10.
Mary is in fact the all-time favorite among girls.
If we look at the popularity over time of these names,
we see that they've gained their spots
in the first half of the 20th century except for Jennifer.
Now that given the structure of the all-time f data frame,
I'm looping over the index rather than the value.
Next, you'll be asked to use what you learned
in a challenge about unisex names.