(playful music)
- [Narrator] For your challenge,
I would like you to find a top ten unisex names
and to plot their popularity throughout the years
for both the male and female usage of the name.
We will define unisex names as those for which
the total number of boys and a total number of girls
born across all years and within a factor of two.
That means that you're going to compute
the total number of boys,
divide by the total number of girls,
and verify that that's between 0.5 and two.
Given the technical nature of some Pandas computations,
I have some hints for you.
Try using DataFrame.groupby().
Take advantage of the fact that Pandas
can execute a mathematical operation between two series
even if they have different indexes.
And finally, if you need to drop not a number,
nan values, use DataFrame.dropna.