(upbeat music)
- As I mentioned already, in Pandas there are often
several ways to get the same result.
So if your results are similar to mine,
but you get them in a different way,
don't worry, your solution may even be better.
We'll load our data set as usual.
We need to compute the total number of boys and girls
for a given name.
This seems a good place to use group by,
which lets us segment the data before applying
an aggregation, in this case, the sum
of the number of babies.
So we use group by over sex and name,
we select the number column and we take the sum.
From this list with a multi-index,
we can grab the males and females respectively,
using dot lock.
As you see, the two indices are going to be different.
Epon doesn't appear in the females.
Nevertheless, we can combine the two series
and pandas will align the indices for us.
The results would be none where either series
doesn't have an element.
For instance we check where the ratio between
males and females is less than two.
We can certainly get rid of those nones
with drop in A.
Now, remember the definition of unisex names
as those with a ratio between .5 and two.
This is a good expression for fancy indexing,
and after we apply it,
we see that 1660 names pass the test.
Here, I've taken the index, because we don't actually need
the ratio itself, but just the names.
The next thing to do is to find the ten most common
unisex names, so we sum the male and female counts
using the unisex array to index our two totals.
We sort the resulting series,
and we cut it off at the top.
Jessie seems to be the winner of this particular contest,
followed by Reilly, Casey, and Jackie.
Now to clock popularity, it's convenient to use
a fully indexed data frame.
We also remember to sort that index.
Now we'll loop over the most common unisex names,
which remember, are the index of the common series,
and we plot by selecting male or female in the name.
Matplotlib type layout helps improve the spacing
of the subplots, while Jessie is the absolute winner,
it appears to have fallen out of favor somewhat.
Reilly is ascendant, but not for boys anymore,
and Casey, which peaked around 1990,
may be the most unisex name of all,
with the male usage of the name tracking the
female usage very closely.
Great, we've been through a lot in this course,
and I hope you've gained an understanding
of what is possible with NumPy and Pandas and matplotlib,
and more generally, with Python as a language
for data analysis.
I hope you'll go out to discover and learn
even more and that you use Python happily
in your every day work.