- [Instructor] For this course,
we need an up to date installation of Python 3,
and a few third party packages including Jupyter, NumPy,
Pandas, and Matplotlib.
In this video I show you how to install everything you need
on MacOS 10.
If you are a Windows user,
feel free to jump to the next video.
Later I will also show you how to use Python in the cloud
using only your web browser.
If you already use Python on your machine
and you know how to install extra packages, please do so.
Otherwise I suggest you follow me
and install the free Anaconda Python Distribution,
which includes everything that we will need.
To install we go to anaconda.com.
We find the download link at the top.
Scroll down to our platform
and select the Anaconda graphical installer
which is currently at version 3.7.
Any later version will also work fine.
As of January 2020, Python 2 is no longer supported,
so you should definitely be using version three
which is mature, efficient,
and introduces many exciting new features
compared to version two.
Once the download has completed,
we click on the installer
and proceed through a standard installation
which will require several clicks.
We are asked also
whether we wish to install the PyCharm IDE,
which is very complete and powerful.
We will not be using it for this course,
but you can give it a try.
We can trash the installer,
and we can now try out our new python installation,
by opening up a terminal and typing Python.
This gets us into the standard Python shell
where we can write an execute code interactively.
The prompt informs us
that this is indeed the Anaconda version of Python 3.7.
It's traditional to just say hello.
We can also verify that all the packages we need
are already installed by attempting to import them.
NumPy, Pandas, and Matplotlib.
No news is good news.
All done.
We are now ready to start experimenting with Python.