- [Narrator] For this course,
we need an up to date installation of python three.
And a few third party packages.
Including jupyter notebook, numpy, pandas,
and matplotlib.
In this video, I show you how to install everything
you need on Windows.
However, you can also experiment with Python in the cloud
from your web browser.
I explain how to do so at the end of this chapter.
If you are already using Python on your machine
and you know how to install extra packages,
you are free to do so.
Otherwise, I suggest you follow me
and install the free Anaconda Python distribution.
Which includes everything that we need.
To install, we go to the anaconda.com website,
we find a download link on the top.
Verify that we have the right platform.
And then download the 64 bit graphical installer.
This is currently at version 3.7,
but any later version will also work fine.
Once the download has completed,
we click on installer and proceed through an installation.
This requires a few clicks.
(mouse clicks)
As of January 2020, Python two is no longer supported.
So you should definitely be using version three.
Which is mature, efficient, and introduces
many exciting new features compared to version two.
The final phase of the installation takes a few minutes.
It looks like the setup is finished,
and we now can get started with Python.
We can now try out our new Python
by opening up the Anaconda prompt,
and typing python.
This gets us into the standard python shell,
where we can write and execute code interactively.
The prompt, informs us that this is indeed
the Anaconda version of Python 3.7
It's traditional to say hello.
We can also verify that all the packages that we need
are already installed by attempt to import them.
Numpy, pandas, and matplotlib.
No news is good news.
All done.
We are now ready to start experimenting with python.