- [Narrator] Jupyter notebooks,
offer a very convenient way to write code,
run it, and collect the results including plots,
in a single document.
You can even write formatted text and equations.
This is my favorite way of using Python,
because it lets me experiment with data and code,
document my work, and go back to it later.
You start Jupiter notebook from the Anaconda navigator,
by clicking on launch.
If you don't have an Anaconda,
you can go to a terminal, and type Jupyter notebook.
A web browser opens, and I can choose
if I wish to load an existing notebook from the file system,
or to start a new one,
which I do at the top right of the screen.
New, Python three notebook.
Here's the notebook. See the green box at the top?.
It's a cell. It's ready for me to write some Python,
for instance,
(keyboard typing)
The customary equating.
I execute the code, by pressing Shift + Enter,
or Shift + return depending on your keyboard.
The output is printed immediately below it.
I can click inside the cell,
modify it,
and execute it again, with shift enter.
If a cell has a blue border,
I need to press ENTER before I can edit it.
Or I can click inside a different cell, to edit that one.
In addition to a simple command,
I can write a function over multiple lines.
The editor, will color the Python source keywords,
appropriately.
Again, I execute with Shift + Enter
cells, can also contain text rather than code.
For that, I can use the drop down menu cell,
to change the cell type to markdown.
Then I click in the cell and start writing.
Markdown is a simple but powerful text format
that can do basic formatting, bold, italic,
bullet points, hyperlinks, and even mathematical formulas.
For instance, bold, (keyboard typing), with two asterisks.
(keyboard typing)
URLs, which are recognized,
a bullet point,
and a formula in the LaTeX language, between dollar signs.
When I execute the cell, with shift Enter,
everything is formatted in prettified.
To copy a cell, I can click inside it,
or use the arrow keys to select it, and then press
escape C, to copy and then escape V, to paste.
To cut a cell, I can do escape X
To delete a cell ctrl M, and then D, and again D,
Jupyter wants to be sure
you really want to delete that cell.
Or you can use the menus, of course,
I gave you only the most useful keyboard shortcuts,
but there are many more, look under the Help menu.
The notebook is saved periodically for us,
but I can also do that at any time with command S,
ah, and I can give this notebook a name,
such as learning Jupyter,
by clicking at the top of the window.
Go find the Jupyter notebook documentation,
at Jupiter.org.
You will also learn about Jupyter lab,
and even more powerful,
and complete interface than notebooks.
For this course however, we will stay with Jupyter notebook.