- [Instructor] For most of the videos in this course,
we will be working through one of the Jupyter Notebooks
that I prepare for you.
For each notebook, we will go through the path
and code that it contains.
We will discuss what the code does
and why I wrote it that way.
We will execute it and examine the resulting output.
At any time, you're welcome to pause the video,
inspect the code, make changes
and run your own experiments.
All the notebooks are collected in your exercise files,
organized by course chapter.
They are the files with .ipynb file ending.
You will also see some of the data files
that we will be analyzing.
In Chapter Five, I have included a subfolder
named Downloaded.
These are files that we will download
from the web using Python,
but I am including them here
in case something goes wrong with the download.
We open a notebook by finding it
within the Jupyter Notebook file browser
and clicking on it.
The notebook cell that we're discussing and running
will always be the one enclosed by a blue or green box.
Once we're done with the notebook,
you can close the browser tab
and shut down the notebook in the Jupyter file browser
by clicking on the box and then clicking Shutdown.