- [Instructor] An exciting, recent development
in the Python ecosystem is that it has become possible
to run notebooks in the cloud using services
such as Google Colaboratory and Microsoft Azure Notebooks.
With both, you get a rather functional environment for free.
If you'd like to follow along with this course
using Python in the cloud,
I suggest you use Azure Notebooks.
Let me show you how to.
We start at notebooks.azure.com.
We sign in, which you can do using
an existing Microsoft account or creating one.
You may also be asked to create a user name
for your profile.
In Azure Notebooks, notebooks are organized in projects,
so we create a new one.
I will call it Python data analysis.
The easiest way to get the exercise files
into Microsoft Azure is to upload the zip file
that contains all of them.
The Upload button is here on the top right.
So I go find a file and upload it.
To unzip the archive, I open the Azure terminal.
I type cd library to move into the project directory
and then unzip exercise\ files.zip.
This will take a moment.
Once it's done, we can type exit,
and close this tab.
If I refresh the window,
I see that the exercise files have appeared.
We are now ready for our course.
For instance, I can look inside the exercise files
for chapter two and select the first notebook.
Azure Notebooks can be somewhat slow when loading
and writing files, but don't worry.
You'll get there.
Also, as we speak, the default Python on Azure is 3.5,
which is too old for this course.
Hopefully that will change soon.
In the meantime, please remember to switch the kernel
to Python 3.6 after you open each notebook.
You do that from the Kernel menu, go into Change kernel,
and select Python 3.6
There are many options out there to use Python in the cloud.
Please feel free to use the one that works out best for you.