- [Instructor] In chapter two,
we have reviewed Python loops,
data containers, and comprehensions.
Now we will set them to work
in a simple, practical project,
finding anagrams in the English dictionary.
As you know, two words are anagrams of each other
when their letters can be rearranged
to turn one word into the other.
For instance, elvis and lives.
We will use this simple strategy to find anagrams.
We defined a signature of a word
as the sorted list of its letters, including duplicates.
So the signature of post would be opst.
And then we find that spot, stop, tops, pots, and opts
have the same signature as post
and therefore they're all anagrams of each other.
We're going to make a Python dict
of all the words in the dictionary indexed by signature.
And then to find out if a word has an anagram,
we will just compute the signature
and look it up in the dict.
Let's begin.