- [Instructor] We begin.
By loading a list of words from a file.
Your exercise files.
Already contain a list that we can use as an example.
The file is words.txt
and it sits in the same folder as this Jupyter notebook.
That file is, in fact, the nineteen thirty four dictionary.
That is distributed with many UNIX systems.
If you wish, you can find a better one and use that instead.
Now in Python.
We talk of idioms
to refer to code constructs.
That have become the preferred way
to achieve a certain goal.
A classical example is looping through
all the lines of a text files.
To do so.
We open the file for reading.
Let's open
with a mode of "R"
and then, we can use the file as an iterable.
In a fold loop.
Which has the result
or giving us the lines one by one.
For the moment.
All that we will do with each line,
is just collect it in a list.
What did we get?
More than two hundred thousand words.
Let's look at the first few using slicing.
As we learned in chapter two.
That's good.
I see two problems though.
Every word ends in the new line character.
Denoted in "C" and in Python
as backslash "n".
Also some of the words are capitalized.
Which will interfere
with our scheme of computing signatures.
We can fix both issues using Python string methods.
To strip leading and trailing whitespace.
Including new lines.
We can apply strip.
let's take our own for example.
The new line is stripped away.
Now to switch the entire string to lowercase.
Who use the method lower.
So now.
There's something more interesting to do
in the body of a loop.
Will append to the empty list
is stripped and lowercase version of each line.
Now I see a duplicate.
Which comes from "a"
appearing both in uppercase and lowercase.
One way to get rid of duplicates
is to build not a list but a set.
so I will do my loop once more.
Replace the empty initial list with the empty set
and replace a pen with ADD
and given that the body of the loop is just one line.
There is an even more
idiomatic way of writing it.
You probably guessed it already as a comprehension.
The comprehension will have
the expression I want to collect
and then the loop over lines in the file.
Here it is.
If we wish to restore the alphabetical order.
We can just wrap the set
in the Python built-in sorted.
Which produces a list.
A list however without duplications.
We are now ready to make Anna Graham's.
By the way.
If you want to try in a different language
such as French.
You can follow along what we did
with the appropriate file.
The good thing is that in Python three
all strings are natively unicode.
Meaning that they can handle
international character sets transparently.
The characters are encoded internally
using multiple bytes as needed.
They only care that we need to take
is to tell Python which encoding to use for
the files we read and write.
There are multiple mappings
between character sets and bytes.
So we need to know which one was used.
Your exercise files include a French dictionary.
Written using
the iso-eighty eight five nine encoding
also known as latin one.
Let's read all of its lines.
In this case instead of a loop.
We use the built-in method with lines.