- [Instructor] We pick up our exercise
where we left it in the last video.
We have made a sorted list of lowercase words.
lets load it up.
Now, remember our strategy of comparing signatures.
Those are the sorted lists
of the component letters of each word.
We need a function to make them.
Taking the string N again as an example,
let's see what happens if we sort it.
Which we do with the built-in sorted.
Indeed, we get a sorted list of the letters,
which is already the signature.
We can use it to verify say
that Elvis is an anagram of lives, but not of sings.
For convenience, we will collate the list
of characters back into a single signature to string.
The way this is achieved in Python looks a little strange,
since we need to call the method join on a string
that specifies the connector so to speak of the join.
If it's a dash, we get a-a-n-o-r.
So the connector we really want is the empty string.
We're ready to make a function
that performs this operation in general.
Now, I remind you that our anagram finding strategy
is to build a dictionary of words indexed by signature.
Of course, we could also try a brute-force search
that loops to the dictionary,
computes the signature for every word
and compares it with the signature
of the word we want to anagram.
That's what find anagram does.
This works and seems fast enough
to see just how fast we can use the IPython magic %time.
So 200 milliseconds, that is not a long time to wait
but we become unbearable if we need
to compute long lists of anagrams.
So let's do this the smart way.
As we said, we will build the Python dict
of words indexed by signatures.
In fact, the values in the dict will be set,
that indeed, contain all the words with the same signature.
We call it words by SIG.
If you think about it,
this is the perfect application for default dict.
Which we introduced in chapter two.
Since the first time that we meet the signature,
we have to somehow produce an empty set
and add to it, perfect.
Perhaps we could perform one last filtering operation
by removing signatures with a single word.
After all, every word is an anagram of itself,
but that's not very interesting.
To do the filtering, we can use a dictionary comprehension.
Remember, to iterate on both key
and value we use dict items.
Then with the clause to select non-trivial anagram sets
will length greater than one.
Excellent, we can allow the simple function
find anagram first that looks up a word
in the dict by signature.
This works fine, let's see for my name.
Nothing, I didn't really expect one,
But perhaps we shouldn't get an error
when no anagram is found just the empty set.
To fix that, we'll use a try except close.
And we'll catch the key error exception with
accept key error and just return the empty set in that case.
If you're not familiar with exceptions in Python,
I encourage you to go look them up
in the Python documentation.
So let's try again to anagram my name and get the empty set.
This new function is much, much faster.
Now that we have set this machinery up,
there are many interesting investigations we could do.
For instance, how about finding the sets
of anagrams with the longest words?
We get that by sorting the signatures,
which we get from keys applied to anagrams
by SIG using length.
So we use the sorted built-in,
given a sorting key of Len and a sync for reverse order.
These are the longest signatures,
but to see the actual anagrams,
we can wrap it in a list comprehension.
The longest anagrams have 22 letters.
Looking at this list though, I must say
that these are compound medical words
that are not too creative in anagrammatical terms.
How about the set of anagrams with the most words?
For this, we will sort the dict values instead of the keys.
And again use Len as the sorting key.
The two longest groups have 10 elements,
though some of these words are not very easily recognizable.
Well done, this completes our exercise.
Next, let's put what you learned to good use
and take on a challenge again about wordplay.