(upbeat music)
- [Narrator] Here is my solution to the challenge.
You were asked to find all palindromic
pairs of words in the English dictionary.
We start by loading our list of words
with the one line of comprehension.
We will explore the fact that if two words are palindromic,
then they are also anagrams of each other.
We will also need the code we wrote in this chapter
to compute signatures
and to associate words to signatures.
In Python, there is no built-in function
or method to reverse a string,
but we can achieve it easily by slicing.
The slicing step will need to be negative backwards.
We will omit the slice start and stop
to get the entire string.
So for Mickela, we do a slice of colon, colon, minus one.
We now look over all the word sets,
one for each signature,
and then overall pairs of words in the word set,
checking if one of them equals the reverse of the other.
It's a little annoying to write the loops,
so that we are only checking the same pair twice,
in reversed orders.
One way is to check pairs on if they are sorted.
Here's the list.
It includes also the true palindromes
where in order, reverse order,
equals itself.
But manual dis-sorts do not seem very common.
I'm going to give you, also, more elegant solution.
Using the stand a library module, intertools.
Intertools includes an iterator combinations
which return all combinations,
say of two items,
from a list of three.
We can then simplify our solution,
by again looping over word sets,
and then by selecting pairs of words in the word set
using intertools combinations.
The code is cleaner and more expressive.
But the solution is the same.