- [Instructor] In this chapter,
we are going to experiment with NumPy
on a real world use case,
analyzing weather data from NOAA,
the National Oceanic and Atmosphere Administration.
The GHCN, the Global Historical Climatology Network Daily
is an integrated database of daily climate summary
from land surface stations across the globe.
Many in big cities for instance.
Climate summaries, in this case,
means variables
such as the minimum and maximum temperatures,
the total precipitation, and so on.
The data files that we will be using
can be obtained from the NOAA website.
Together we will download a station list
and use it to locate temperature data for cities.
We will load the data files, fill missing values,
and smooth time series.
Finally,
we will create a visualization of daily temperatures
inspired by the New York Times weather plots.