- [Instructor] In this chapter,
we download several data files from the web.
However, all the files that we analyze
are also included in your exercise files,
in case they became unavailable online,
or you're unable to download them for any other reason.
And before we load the data itself,
it's also a good idea
to start by looking at it's documentation.
Browsing through the file listing at the NOAA website,
we see a README file, and we start there.
Instead of clicking on that link in our browser,
let's use Python to download the file.
There are several Python modules we could use,
but for a simple download,
the standard library module, urllib,
is quite appropriate.
urllib.request.urlretrieve needs the URL
and the name of a local file.
It's done already.
We can use the Jupyter Notebook
to look at the README file, by clicking on it.
We see that it describes the contents of the directory,
the format of DLY data files,
which contain data for a single station,
and are formatted with fixed-width columns.
And the format of a file, GHCND stations,
thank you, says the location, elevation, and ID
for each station in the network.
That's where we need to start,
so we download that file with urllib.
I've copied the description of the format
into a text field in this Notebook,
for our reference.
To load a fixed-width text file, such as this,
we can use NumPy genfromtxt.
It needs rather precise information.
We specify the width of each field
in the parameter delimiter.
We can derive the widths from the table above,
or we need to increase them
to include the spaces between the columns.
Next, we provide the name,
a descriptive name for each column.
And we specify the dtype,
the NumPy data type for each column.
For the first field, for instance,
we need a string of 11 characters.
Then, we have three floats,
and a few more strings of various lengths.
And last, we'll tell NumPy
to remove all the leading and trailing spaces
from all the strings it parses.
There result is a NumPy record array
with more than a hundred thousand entries.
Thankfully, Jupyter chooses to show us only a few lines
at the top and the bottom.
By plotting longitude against latitude,
we get an idea of the impressive global coverage
of the database.
We need to make the dots small,
so that they're not too crowded.
Even so, the US and Europe are basically
just solid masses of ink.
How about stations in California?
We can use fancy indexing with a Boolean expression,
stations state equals equals CA
to downselect our dataset.
Coverage is still impressive.
What if we need a specific station?
Fancy indexing again comes to the rescue.
We select all stations,
for which it is true that the name field equals 'Pasadena'.
We find one.
If we want all stations that start with a given string,
the syntax would be more esoteric.
What np.char.find does,
is to return the index at which a certain substring,
'Pasadena' in this case,
appears in the field,
or minus one if the substring is not there.
If we required the index to be zero,
that's the same as saying
that the station name begins with 'Pasadena'.
So, we see that there are several stations,
a few of them in Pasadena, Texas and Pasadena, Maryland.
Only one, however,
is in the quality-controlled HCN network.
Let's get that one.
I've built this URL by looking at the structure
of the directories on the website.
You see that it ends in Pasadena's ID, USC00046719.dly.
Locally, we'll download to the file Pasadena.dly.
Let's look at that file.
Again, with Jupyter Notebook.
It's quite messy, but we recognize the station ID
in the beginning of each line,
followed by year and month.
Here, we are in 1918.
The name of an element, such as TMAX,
and 31 data points, one for each day of the month.
Each data point itself,
consists of the value and three flags.
We could use genfromtxt again,
but it's going to take us a while,
so, I prepared a small module for you, getweather.py,
that takes care of parsing the file
and returning consecutive daily values for a year.
The module uses Pandas to clean and reformat data,
but returns it as a pure NumPy array.
After you've learned about Pandas later in this course,
I encourage you to go look at getweather.py
and see what I did there.
We import the module
and then we look at the help, known as docstring.
This function does what I described,
returning data for one year, for one station.
Let's try it out on Pasadena.
We request both TMIN and TMAX for year 2000.
Some measurements are missing,
and they are here represented as 'nan', nan, not a number.
This function would be a great foundation
for our work in the next few videos.