- [Instructor] We pick up where we left
and load temperature data for Pasadena, California
using our getweather module.
This is a time series, a sequence of values,
organized chronologically, usually with equal cadence,
that is the same time interval
between every two consecutive samples.
To get a sense of the data, one of them begins
by computing its average value
and perhaps its extreme, the minimum and maximum.
With NumPy, we can use mean, min, and max.
But wait, in this case, we seem to get NaNs.
What's going on?
It shouldn't be surprising, if we remember
that the data contains missing values,
which are indeed represented as NaNs.
And NaNs can't really participate
in any mathematical operation, NaN plus one is still NaN.
In fact, how many do we have?
The NumPy function isnan,
creates a Boolean array of NaN-ness, so to speak.
We can then count the instances of true
in this array by using a neat trick.
If we do arithmetics with Booleans in Python,
they are converted to integers
with false counting as zero and true as one.
So, for instance, false plus true plus true is two.
It follows that we can count the trues
in a Boolean array just by summing it up with NumPy sum.
So what can we do?
Missing values are so common, in fact,
the NumPy offers versions of its functions
that simply ignore them.
For instance, NumPy nanmin and nanmax.
If we do need an uninterrupted series of numbers,
we could just set the NaNs to the average of the column.
This is yet another application of fancy indexing
because we want to modify only the NaN elements.
So we write something like Pasadena to mean
fancy indexed to the true NaN Boolean mask
is set equal to the NaN mean of the same variable.
This works fine.
We can tell which elements we changed
because they have more digits than all the others,
which were encoded with limited precision
in the GHCN data.
The integrated dataset can now be plotted
without discontinuities.
A more powerful approach to restoring missing values
is to interpolate.
That is, we can use neighbor values
to compute a plausible number
for the values that are missing.
Let me demonstrate in a tall problem.
Let's say we measure a function y,
defined at integers x between zero and eight,
but we don't have some of the values.
In this case, we don't have value set x
of two, three, and six.
Let me show you all of this in a plot.
I will now define an array of the integers
at which we do want new interpolated values.
I use NumPy linspace, so if I sat down
and I said zero and eight, it's nine elements total.
The function of NumPy interp takes as arguments
the desired location, my xnew, followed by the data we have,
x and y.
It returns values that are interpolated linearly
by fitting segments between existing data points.
Here I'm plotting interpolated points as orange squares.
This seems to make sense and to be rather conservative.
The newx sequence, if you needed to,
could well be the answer.
30 points between zero and eight.
So let's use interpolation to fill missing values
in the Pasadena temperature data.
I need to load it again, since I fixed it already
by replacing NaNs with nints.
Here, now it's broken again, so to interpolate,
we select the good data points, those that are not NaNs,
and a tilde in this expression denotes logical notation.
Then we make an array of the x-values
for which we want interpolation.
All days from one through 365,
and then we can apply NumPy interp.
This seems to work well.
We celebrate by generalizing our Pasadena-centric code,
so that it can fill up holes in any array by interpolation.
It's just a question of replacing Pasadena
with a generic array argument, and 365
with the length of that array.
Finally, we can plot interpolated temperature series
in all their glory using our new function.