- [Instructor] Now we know how to load
temperature data from any station,
how to compute basic summaries
such as mean, min and max,
and how to integrate missing data points
using interpolation.
We'll continue with more data analysis in NumPy.
I've copied your fill NaNs function here
since we will need it.
We looked at data for Pasadena in the last video,
now let's move to even sunnier skies
by looking at weather in the town of Hilo,
big island Hawaii.
We use our custom loader
and again, I encourage you to go look under the hood.
This is data in fact from Hilo International Airport
we now fill the missing data for both T min and T max.
Once more two pole unpacking is very useful.
Let's look at some data summaries.
The yearly average which gives us a sense
of the typical value for T min, and it's min and max.
Will span the range of variation of these measurements.
We can plot the summaries together with the time series.
The map load live function adds each line,
plots a horizontal line that spans the entire graph.
Also useful for reference values,
and we'll make them dotted.
Another common way to measure the range of variation
of a time series is to compute the standard deviation
defined at the square root of the values.
If you don't know about this you can go to statistics,
text book, or to Wikipedia.
Mean and variance are computed in NumPy with NP Mean
and NP Var, we can plot the time series again
using the mean and the mean minus
and plus the standard deviation as references.
Most of the time the temperatures are included in this range
and given that this is Hawaii it's also interesting
to look at precipitation.
We grab those values with Get Weather and just plot them.
The rainy season starting in November is quite evident.
Now looking at the data this way is very informative,
but we also see lots of noise, rapid variations between
one day and the next, which can obscure underlying trends.
To remove the noise, we can smooth the data.
So that we see the slower long-term behavior
below those still issues and the simplest approach
to smoothing is replacing each value with the average
of a set of its neighbors.
With NumPy we can do this with correlate.
I will demonstrate first with a very simple
and short data set consisting of two peaks
over a background of zeroes.
I then define a roughly triangular correlation mask
which is highest in the middle and drops down to the sides
and I have arranged the values so they sum to one,
next I write the correlation.
What it does is to multiply each element
in the series with the mask
and then sum up all the resulting short series.
Sliding them so they are centered around the sample
that we multiply, thus as you see in this figure,
each peak generates a triangle centered
on its location.
I have not explained the keyword same that we gave
to correlate, what it does is to request that
the output of the correlation be the same length
as the input.
Even as this means that the points on the boundaries
get sums from fewer masks.
So we may see some anomaly there.
To smooth our temperature series we will use
an even simpler mask, uniform values normalized
so that they sum to one.
We're going to get that in NumPy with NumPy once,
let's try this out.
We plot the regional temperature series as dots,
maybe a little smaller than usual,
and the smoothed series has a continuous line.
This works fine, we are reducing oscillations
while emphasizing the underlying slower trend.
We do see something strange happening
at the beginning and end of the data set.
The values are going way low.
That has to do with the keyword same,
and we detect that the values on the boundaries
have fewer neighbors than everybody else.
If we can do without a few points at the end
and at the beginning we can change our request
to amply correlate to valid and avoid this problem.
We can now make a function to apply smoothing
of any length to any array.
The length of the smoothing mask is sometimes called window
and by default we'll use valid mode.
We then plot T min and T max together for Hilo.
It's an interesting plot
and I'd like to see it for other cities,
so once again let's take a code
and generalize it to arbitrary station and year.
So we get the data, we fill in the NaNs
and we plot both the original data and a smooth version.
We need to offset the plot a bit since we lose points
with valid mode, so the range if the smoothing is over
20 days would just be from day 10
to day 356 of the year.
Let me try this out, for instance over multiple years
for Hilo to see if the Hawaii climate is stable.
Quite so.
How about comparing cities in different climates?
Let me look over Pasadena, New York, San Diego,
and Minneapolis and then create a sub-plot
in two rows and two columns for each one of them.
I'll focus on the year 2000.
There's some downloading and then we see the plots
come out together, if you can choose based on weather alone
where would you live?