- [Instructor] We're going to conclude a NumPy practice,
by making a quick but impressive weather visualization,
that showcases the power
and flexibility of NumPy and Matplotlib.
It's inspired by the New York Times
weather chart shown here.
And it shows daily minima and maxima,
the proper band in the context of their normal range,
dark gray and of their records, light gray.
We will again use Pasadena as an example,
but you can do your own city,
if it's included in the NOAA data set.
Remember, we want to show Records,
which means that we need all the data we can get.
The Gateway, the module,
that's a query for one year of data at a time.
So, we'll call it repeatedly collecting the results
in a comprehension and feeding that to NumPy vstack,
which makes a two-dimensional array formally
so one-dimensional arrays.
The result can be visualized with matchshow.
We've added also a colored bar to provide a reference
of the mapping of values to color.
And we have specified the extent
to get more informative labels on the axis.
We see some missing data, the white patches,
and we can observe winter and summer nights getting warmer
towards the end of the century.
For simplicity, we will forego filling a nance
and use NaN robust functions.
We want record temperatures for every day of the year.
This means that we can use NumPy nanmin on the demand data
and specify axis equals zero,
so that the minimum will be taken
across all rows for each column.
We do the same for tmax using NumPy nanmax.
Let's see the records.
Now for the normals.
In the New York Times plot the normal temperature range
for each day is defined as the average
of the low and high from 1981 to 2010.
So we build another stacked array with a reduced year range.
And again, we take nan robust means, across rows.
So that's axis equals zero.
Here's the normal range.
We're ready to get the plot together.
We do Pasadena in 2018, just like the Times,
so I'd better get that data.
To plot the band,
we use Micro-LIBS fill between which needs an x-axis
to coordinate the array.
It needs also the lower
and upper lines that delimit the band.
So for the x-axis,
I will use the day of the year for one to 365.
Here it is, I will do similar bands
for the records and normal ranges.
I also want to show the average temperature for the year.
I have to compute that though.
That would be the mean of the minimum temperature
plus the mean of the maximum
all across the year, divided by two.
In 2018,
that was 19.46 degrees Celsius.
I'm going to put this average temperature in the title,
so I need to build up a string for that.
For that, I will use the very convenient formatted string
literals introduced in Python 3.6.
If I start the string with an "F" before the quotes,
I can include variable names in braces,
which are then replaced by their values.
I can also specify formatting instructions as I would,
using the string format interface.
For instance, two decimal digits
for the average temperature.
Let me put everything together.
I plot the three bands for record normal and current year.
I have also looked up the red green blue,
the composition of the New York Times colors,
which Matplotlib bonds as values between zero and one.
The optional step equals myth makes the band look blocky
so the individual days are in evidence.
And last, the alpha setting makes
the current year band partially transparent.
I set reasonable access limit and finally add a title.
Let's fire it off, very nice.
In 2018, some values are missing,
we see the purple band is interrupted
and those are actually the hottest days.
So you can play with other cities we'll turn this example
into a function that can plot any year in any station.
So here's New York in 2018.
NumPy is extremely powerful and flexible,
so you should learn about it in depth.
Coupled with Matplotlib it offers a direct route
to beautiful and informative visualizations.
In my course, Python Statistics Essential Training,
explores statistical plots in more detail
and with more examples.
You are now ready for your challenge.