(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] We start by importing getWeather,
since we need temperature data.
It will also be good to show smoothed plots,
so we'll grab the smooth function that we made.
We need all the available historical data for New York,
say 1880 through 2019,
which we collect in a stacked array.
We sum TMIN and TMAX for this large array
and then take the average across the columns.
So x is equal one,
so that we get a value for each year.
The shape isn't yet what we expect.
Next, the mid-century average.
We need to figure out the index of 1945 and 1955,
in this all avg array.
For lists, we can use index
to figure out the location of an element.
But unfortunately,
that doesn't work for NumPy arrays.
However, we can turn array into lists quite easily
by feeding them to the list constructor,
and then index works.
So now we can perform the mid-century average
over the correct slice of the array.
It's 12.8 degrees.
And here's the plot.
The anomaly is all avg
minus the mid-century mean.
It's quite noisy,
so let's smooth it out.
If we use valid mode to avoid artifacts at the edges,
we need to remove some years from the x-coordinate.
The solution is complete really,
but we can collect this code in a more general function
so we can compare a few cities.
So here's the comparison,
with some complaints from NumPy
by way of Jupiter
that there's really no data before 1910 for Pasadena,
and 1940 for Minneapolis.
Still, the upward trend for all these three locations
is quite evident.